"Why the IQs of Vegetarian
Children Are Higher"
Many vegetarian parents believe
their children are brighter
than omnivorous kids,
but you don't really know
until you put it to the test.
And, indeed,
the IQ of vegetarian children
tested about 16 points
higher than average,
and their mental age exceeded
their chronological age
by about a year.
The researchers knew
the veg kids were bright,
but why were they
so much more superior?
There are obviously
confounding factors,
like maybe more highly
educated parents
are more likely to have
vegetarian children,
and they pass down both
their brains and their diets.
Even if there is
a cause-and-effect relationship
between vegetarianism and IQ,
were the children smarter
because they were vegetarians,
or did they become vegetarian
because they were so smart?
Researchers in the UK followed
8,000 kids for decades.
They measured their IQ
at age 10,
then came back 20 years later
and asked which of them had
become vegetarian during that time.
And, indeed, the smarter kids
had an increased likelihood
of being a vegetarian
as an adult.
The researchers even quoted
Benjamin Franklin,
saying that vegetarian
diets result in
"Greater clearness of head
and quicker comprehension."
According to the largest
and oldest association
of nutrition professionals
in the world,
strictly plant-based
diets are appropriate
for all stages of
the life cycle,
including childhood,
and may indeed
provide health benefits.
What about plant-based diets
and growth in children?
Some studies show that children
raised on restrictive
macrobiotic diets
suffer from growth stunting,
while others show
that those raised plant-based
may end up being
up to an inch (2.5 cm) taller.
In a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of children on vegan diets,
heights were lower in vegans,
but only because
they included a study
in which the vegan kids
were significantly younger,
mostly 10 to 14 years old,
compared to mostly
15 to 19 years old.
Once you remove the study
with the age disparity,
the height disparity
also disappears.
What about width disparity?
Population studies indicate
that vegetarian diets
are associated with
a lower prevalence of obesity
in both adults and children.